Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio and Television Department Records, 1932-1978 and undated RL.11008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio/Television Department records
1932-1978 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio and Television Department
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.11008
15 Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Collection spans 1932-1978 and includes correspondence, contracts, reports, surveys, radio and television program scripts and other materials that document the operations of the JWT Radio and Television Department. The bulk of the materials pertain to interactions with several labor unions representing the interests of actors, writers and others involved in radio and television broadcast production, including: American Federation of Musicians (AFM), American Federation of Radio Artists (AFRA, later the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists--AFTRA), Producer-Composers and Lyricists Guild of America (P-CLGA), Radio-TV Directors Guild (RTDG), the Screen Actors Guild (SAG, later merged with AFTRA to form SAG-AFTRA), and the Television Authority. Sponsor companies represented include Ballantine, Ford, Kodak, Kraft, Lever (Unilever), Quaker Oats and Schlitz. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sale, Advertising & Marketing History.
Historical note
Organizational timeline
1933 Screen Actors Guild (SAG) founded
1937 American Federation of Radio Artists (AFRA) founded
1948 Radio Directors Guild (RDG) changes name to Radio and Television Directors Guild (RTDG)
1949 The Television Authority (TvA) is formed
1952 The AFRA and TvA merge to form the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA)
1960 The RTDG merges with the Screen Directors Guild (SDG) to form the Directors Guild of America (DGA)
1962 JWT establishes the Radio and Television Department
1974 SAG and AFTRA conduct the first joint negotiation for prime time network contracts
1981 SAG and AFTRA enter into merger "Phase I" talks, but action is halted by an anti-trust suit
2012 SAG and AFTRA finally merge to form SAG-AFTRA
Collection Overview
Collection spans 1932-1978 and includes correspondence, contracts, reports, surveys, radio and television program scripts and other materials that document the operations of the JWT Radio and Television Department. The bulk of the materials pertain to interactions with several labor unions representing the interests of actors, writers and others involved in radio and television broadcast production, including: American Federation of Musicians (AFM), American Federation of Radio Artists (AFRA, later the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists--AFTRA), Producer-Composers and Lyricists Guild of America (P-CLGA), Radio-TV Directors Guild (RTDG), the Screen Actors Guild (SAG, later merged with AFTRA to form SAG-AFTRA), and the Television Authority. Sponsor companies represented include Ballantine, Ford, Kodak, Kraft, Lever (Unilever), Quaker Oats and Schlitz. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sale, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Commercial Talent Contractors, Inc.; General Television; Card Files; Scripts; Television Programs by Sponsor; and Unions.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio and Television Department Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1987
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following collections of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives held in the Hartman Center:
16mm Microfilm As-Broadcast
Carroll Carroll Papers
John F. Devine Papers
Maury Holland Papers
Dan Seymour Papers
Edward G. Wilson Papers
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Labor unions -- United States; Radio programs -- United States; Radio broadcasting -- United States; Radio programs; Radio advertising -- United States; Radio broadcasting; Radio advertising; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising -- United States; Advertising; Radio scripts; Television advertising; Television advertising -- United States; Television programs; Television scripts; Television programs -- United States; Television broadcasting; Television broadcasting -- United States; Labor unions; J. Walter Thompson Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Eastman Kodak Company; SAG-AFTRA (Organization); Screen Actors Guild; Quaker Oats Company; Unilever (Firm); Kraft Foods Company; Ford Motor Company; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists; American Federation of Musicians; P. Ballantine & Sons; Jos. Schlitz Brewing Co.
- Commercial Talent Contractors, Inc. (CTC), 1961-1973; 1
  - Drafts of contracts, 1961-1962, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Kraft, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--Procedure memo, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Finance--Tax withholding material, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Ford--Ford Festival (James McHaj), 1951 (Box 1)
  - Ford--Ford Star Revue (Jack Haley, Kay Kiser), 1950 (Box 1)
  - Ford--Kay Kiser Show, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
- General Television Related, 1949-1975, bulk 1950s; 2
  - Exporting filmed commercials to Canada, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Ford--Milton, Pee Pars, Marshall, Screen Gems, 1952 (Box 1)
  - JWT Folio Form Book, 1958 (Box 2)
  - JWT/New York Television Production, 1975 (Box 2)
  - TV Workshop Demonstration, press conference and luncheon, 1955 (Box 2)
- Card Files, 1951-1957; 3
  - Index to Lux Radio Theatre Plays A-Z, undated (Box 3)
  - Talent Showcase A-N, 1951-1957 (Box 3)
  - Talent Showcase O-Z, 1951-1957 (Box 3)
- Scripts, 1932-1952; 4
  - Life and Love of Dr. Susan, 1939 Sept.-Oct. (Box 4)
  - Life and Love of Dr. Susan, 1939 Sept.-Dec. (Box 5)
  - Laura Limited--As Broadcast, 1949 Jul. 4-Nov. 30; 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Laura Limited--As Broadcast, 1949 Dec. 1-1950 Apr. 28; 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Laura Limited--As Broadcast, 1950 May 1-Sept. 1; 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Laura Limited--As Broadcast, 1950 Sept. 4-1951 Feb. 28; 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Laura Limited--As Broadcast, 1951 Mar. 1-Aug. 31; 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Laura Limited--As Broadcast, 1951 Sept. 3-1952 Feb. 28; 8 folders (Box 11)
  - Vallee Hour Drama (bound scripts), 1932 Nov.-1933 Dec. (Box 12)
  - Vallee Hour Drama (bound scripts), 1933 Dec.-1935 Oct. and undated (Box 13)
  - Vallee Hour Drama (bound scripts), 1936 July 2-1937 Sept. 23 (Box 14)
- Television Programs By Sponsor, 1958-1960; 5
  - Eastman Kodak--Annual Report, 1958 (Box 15)
  - Eastman Kodak--Call reports, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Eastman Kodak--Disneyland special, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Eastman Kodak--Ed Sullivan Show, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Eastman Kodak--General, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Eastman Kodak--Nielsen ratings, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Eastman Kodak--Ozzie & Harriet, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Eastman Kodak--Talent Associates Limited, undated (Box 15)
  - Eastman Kodak--Television advertising budget, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Ford--1960 Ford television presentation, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Ford--General, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Ford--Radio, 1959 (Box 16)
  - Ford--Wagon Train, 1959 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Canada, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Color, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Commercial elements, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Contract, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Correspondence (Hubbell Robinson), 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Format, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--General, 1959-1960; 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Markets, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--MCA personalities proposal, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--MCA presentation, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Music, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ford "Startime"--Production personnel biographies, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Ford "Startime"--Program costs, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Ford "Startime"--Program reports, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Ford "Startime"--Program schedules, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Ford "Startime"--Proposals, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Ford "Startime"--Publicity and promotion, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Ford "Startime"--Research, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Ford "Startime"--Story outlines, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Ford "Startime"--Title, 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - Kraft--Bat Masterson, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Kraft--[Perry] Como Show, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Kraft--Dave King Show, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Kraft--General, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Kraft--Milton Berle/Kraft Music Hall, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Kraft--Nielsen data, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Kraft--Roncom, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Lever Brothers Co, 1959; 11 folders (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Benny Gobel, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Lever Brothers--Call reports, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Lever Brothers--General, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Haggis Baggis, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Have Gun Will Travel, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Hennessey, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Keep Talking, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Radio, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Rawhide, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Sports, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Lever Brothers--Stripe, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Quaker Oats--General, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Quaker Oats--Naked City shooting reports, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Quaker Oats--Ozzie & Harriet, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Quaker Oats--Product allocation schedules, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Quaker Oats--Recommendations for nighttime television, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Quaker Oats--Walt Disney Presents, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Schlitz--Call reports, 1959; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Schlitz--General, 1959 (Box 19)
  - Schlitz--Markham, 1958-1959 (Box 19)
  - Schlitz--Schlitz Playhouse, 1959 (Box 19)
- Unions, 1941-1978; 6
  - AFM--Codes, 1954-1969; 3 folders (Box 19)
  - AFM--Codes, 1969-1975 (Box 20)
  - AFM--Film labor agreement, 1959-1964 (Box 20)
  - AFM--Codes, 1969-1975 (Box 20)
  - AFM--Health and welfare, 1973 (Box 20)
  - AFM--Independent theatricals and television films, 1974-1976 (Box 20)
  - AFM--Letter of adherence, television and radio jingles, spot announcements, 1959 (Box 20)
  - AFM--Live radio and television agreement, 1968-1970 (Box 20)
  - AFM--Memos distributed re AFM (Box 20)
  - AFM--National and local radio and television agreements, 1971 (Box 20)
  - AFM--National radio and television agreements, 1968-1974; 2 folders (Box 20)
  - AFM--Radio, television and film agreements, 1951-1954 (Box 20)
  - AFM--Radio, television and film agreements, 1954-1962; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - AFM--Summary of AFM agreement covering staff and casual musicians in New York and Los Angeles, 1972-1974 (Box 21)
  - AFM--Summary of phonograph agreement, 1973-1975 (Box 21)
  - AFM--Summary of phonograph record label agreement, 1972-1973 (Box 21)
  - AFM--Summary of theatrical and motion picture film agreement, 1972-1974 (Box 21)
  - AFM--Television film labor agreement, 1951-1954 (Box 21)
  - AFM--Videotape agreement, 1972-1974 (Box 21)
  - P-CLGA--Agreement, 1967-1969 (Box 21)
  - RTDG--Agreements, 1954-1956 (Box 21)
  - RTDG--Agreements, 1956-1958 (Box 22)
  - RTDG--Correspondence, 1953-1962 (Box 22)
  - RTDG--Negotiations re code, 1959-1960 (Box 22)
  - RTDG--Network non-custom VT commercial code, 1959-1960 (Box 22)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local, 1973 (Box 23)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Atlanta, 1967-1974; 2 folders (Box 23)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Boston, 1965-1966 (Box 23)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Chicago, 1967-1976; 2 folders (Box 23)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Chicago--Ford radio testimonial problem, 1964 (Box 23)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Cleveland, 1961-1969; 2 folders (Box 23)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Dallas, 1968-1972; 2 folders (Box 23)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Dallas, 1969-1973(4 folders) (Box 24)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Detroit, 1954-1966; 2 folders (Box 24)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Hawaii, 1971; 2 folders (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Los Angeles, 1967 (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Miami, 1966 (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--New Orleans, 1966-1973 (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--New York, 1958-1960 (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Northwest Council of Advertising Agencies, 1966-1972; 2 folders (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Northwest region, 1974 (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Philadelphia, 1969-1972 (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Pittsburgh, 1958-1963; 3 folders (Box 25)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Pittsburgh, 1964-1975; 5 folders (Box 26)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--San Francisco, 1968-1971 (Box 26)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Seattle, 1966 (Box 26)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--St. Louis, 1966-1968 (Box 26)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Twin Cities, 1964-1965 (Box 26)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Local--Washington/Baltimore, 1972-1975 (Box 26)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--National, 1941-1954; 2 folders (Box 26)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--National, 1954-1969; 6 folders (Box 27)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--National, 1966-1972; 2 folders (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--National--Comparision of differences in 1958-1960 AFTRA tape, AFTRA transcription and SAG film commercial codes, undated (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Codes--Non-broadcast, 1977-1978 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Ballantine beer, Use of transcriptions on Yankees broadcasts, 1954 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Continental Airlines, AFTRA claim regarding Shields family, 1963 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--DuPont, WQXR investment program, 1958-1959 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Ford, Settlement for use of Ford spots on Monitor, 1956 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Ford Dealer Association, Pre-season and season sponsorship of Boston Red Sox games, 1958 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Kraft, AFTRA letter of Adherence, 1973 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Libby Macneil Libby, AFTRA claim regarding four commercials taped in Tijuana, Mexico, 1965 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Liebmann/Rheingold, AFTRA settlement, 1963 (Box 28)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Monroe, Transcribed radio over-payments, 1975 (Box 29)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Multiple (Ford Pinto, Blue Cross, Seven Up), Transcribed radio SFO claims, 1971 (Box 29)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Shell, Correspondence with AFTRA regarding locals, 1954-1956 (Box 29)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Companies--Standard Brands, Mystery Voices (Hank Selverstone), 1961 (Box 29)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Industry summaries, 1966-1969; 2 folders (Box 29)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Negotiations file, 1966-1969; 3 folders (Box 29)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Negotiations file, 1966-1969 (Box 30)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Sample scripts, radio and television, 1966-1969 (Box 30)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Television commercial contracts, 1969-1972; 3 folders (Box 30)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Transcriptions ET code negotiations, 1966-1969; 3 folders (Box 31)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Videotape production contract, 1960-1962; 2 folders (Box 31)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Waiver for Campbell-Taggart, 1972 (Box 31)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Contracts--Waivers and interpretations, 1955-1968; 4 folders (Box 32)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Correspondence, 1943-1964; 8 folders (Box 34)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Correspondence--General, 1943-1952 (Box 32)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Correspondence--General, 1943-1952; 3 folders (Box 33)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Correspondence--Legal Department memos and procedures, 1953-1954; 2 folders (Box 33)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Correspondence--Sub-committee file, 1961-1964 (Box 33)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Correspondence--U.S. Committee for Refugees, 1960 (Box 33)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Material concerning tape television commercials, 1958 (Box 33)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Miscellaneous, 1952-1965; 3 folders (Box 34)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Miscellaneous--Television, 1952-1957; 2 folders (Box 34)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Survey by 4-A's (American Association of Advertising Agencies), 1965 (Box 34)
  - SAG/AFTRA--Survey by 4-A's (American Association of Advertising Agencies), 1965-1968; 5 folders (Box 35)
  - TvA--Codes, 1950-1952 (Box 35)
  - TvA--Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 35)